<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discription and breefe discourse, of a most lamentable voiage, made latelie to Tripolie in Barbarie, in a ship named the Iesus vvherin is not onely shevved the great miserie, that then happened the aucthor hereof and his whole companie, aswell the marchants as the marriners in that voiage, according to the curssed custome of those barbarous and cruell tyrants, in their terrible vsage of Christian captiues: but also, the great vnfaithfulnesse of those heathnish infidels, in not regarding their promise. Together, with the most wonderfull iudgement of God, vpon the king of Tripolie and his sonne, and a great number of his people, being all the tormentors of those English captiues. Set foorth by Thomas Saunders, one of those captiues there at the same time.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837459</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837459</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1780</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11529)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1780)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1006:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discription and breefe discourse, of a most lamentable voiage, made latelie to Tripolie in Barbarie, in a ship named the Iesus vvherin is not onely shevved the great miserie, that then happened the aucthor hereof and his whole companie, aswell the marchants as the marriners in that voiage, according to the curssed custome of those barbarous and cruell tyrants, in their terrible vsage of Christian captiues: but also, the great vnfaithfulnesse of those heathnish infidels, in not regarding their promise. Together, with the most wonderfull iudgement of God, vpon the king of Tripolie and his sonne, and a great number of his people, being all the tormentors of those English captiues. Set foorth by Thomas Saunders, one of those captiues there at the same time.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Iones, for Edward White, dwelling at the signe of the Gun, by the little North doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the 15. of Aprill. 1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The voiage of the Iesus into Tripolie in Barbarie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Slavery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tripoli --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tripoli --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Slavery --  Africa, North --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1780:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1780:1"/>
            <p>A true Diſcription and breefe Diſcourſe, Of a moſt lamentable Voiage, made latelie to Tripolie in Barbarie, in a Ship named the IESVS: wherin is not onely ſhewed the great miſerie, that then happened the Aucthor hereof and his whole companie, aſwell the Marchants as the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in that Voiage, according to the curſſed cuſtome of thoſe barbarous and cruell Tyrants, in their terrible vſage of Chriſtian captiues: but alſo, the great vnfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thoſe heathniſh Infidels, in not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding their promiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together, with the moſt woonderfull iudgement</hi> of God, vpon the king of Tripolie and his ſonne, and a great number of his people, being all the Tormentors of thoſe Engliſh Captiues.</p>
            <p>Set foorth by THOMAS SAVNDERS, one of thoſe Captiues there at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by Richard Iones, for Edward White, dwelling at the Signe of the Gun, by the little North doore of Paules, the 15. of Aprill. 1587.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1780:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1780:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worſhipfull Maiſter Iulius Caeſar, doctor of the ciuill law, and Iudge of the Admiraltie: Thomas Saunders wiſheth all health, wealth, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ngratitude or vnthankefulnes for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits receiued (right worſhipfull) is, and euer hath beene a thing ſo lothſom and vile to men of good minds, that (among ſome nations) they haue ſet downe lawes and ordinances to puniſh the offenders therein, ſo hard and ſharpe, that thoſe that haue beene found within the compaſſe of the ſame, haue ſuffered no leſſe then loſſe of life: yea more then this, the verie brute beaſts haue ſo much loathed this horrible vice, that they according to the inſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature, haue ſhewed themſelues (in this reſpect) more indifferent then ſome men: as it is reported in Gueuarra his workes, of a Lion, who finding in his den a fugitiue bondman that was fled from his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, a Romaine Proconſul, dwelling in the confines of the deſarts of Aegipt, hauing hurt his foote with a thorne which he had gotten roming vp and downe ſeeking his praie, ſuffered the ſame to be lanced, cut, and cured by this fugitiue, ſo that within ſhort ſpace it was throughlie whole and well. This poore man although he dwelt quietlie with his new found hoaſt, and might alſo vſe and take ſuch as he got in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, yet louing libertie, on a time g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t foorth of the
<pb facs="tcp:1780:3"/> den, and being ſeene of the eſpials which his maiſter had laide for him, was by them taken and brought to him, who cauſed him to be ſent to Rome, to be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented among other condemned men, at ſuch time as the Emperour ſhould make anie ſolemne feaſt or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. It fortuned afterward, this ſame Lion to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſent alſo to Rome, to be there kept among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſauadge and wilde beaſts. Not long after this, the ſame condemned bondman, was amongſt others ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed alſo to the ſlaughter, &amp; brought into the field called Campus Circulus, to trie his fortune with ſome wild beaſt, and to conclude, it was his good hap to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with that Lion which hee before had cured: Aſſoone as this hungrie ramping Lion had eſpied that man, as one deſirous of his praie, he ran towards him to haue deuoured him, but when hee perceiued well that he was the verie man that had lodged with him in his den, and done him good, he ſtraightwaie ſtood ouer the man, defending him from the crueltie of anie other beaſt. When the man who exſpected nothing but death, had well conſidered the humanitie of the beaſt, and throughlie regarded him, he was then aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it was his quondam hoſte in the deſerts, and therevpon made the bolder to touch him, and ſo ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and cheriſhed him. The Emperour and the whole ſtate of Rome ſtood ſtill, abaſhed at this ſtrange &amp; rare ſight, and after a little ſtaie made, cauſed to be inquired of the man, whether he were a Nigromancer, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had inchanted the Lion, ſeeing that he was hunger-prickt, and yet had no power to hurt him: to this he anſwered, that his ſafetie came by the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the beaſt, and not of anie power of his owne, and reported at large the cauſe of that clemencie, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:1780:3"/> is expreſſed. To be ſhort, the man had his life, and licence to beg vp and downe the ſtreets of Rome, leading the Lion in his hand, vpon whoſe breaſt was written as followeth. Hic Leo eſt hoſpes, huius hominis. and in the forepart of his coate was ſet downe, Hic homo eſt medicus huius Leonis. To auoid this horrible ſinne, I haue (Right worſhipfull) preſumed to dedicate vnto your worſhip, the true reports of my troubles, &amp; of certeine others in Turkie, which although they be not ſet out with braue termes, yet is in them ſet downe nothing but plaine troth, eaſie to be told, but hard to be tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: beſeeching your worſhip, as fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlie to accept of the ſame, as I willinglie preſent it, which if it were anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to my deſires, ſhould then ſignifie what heart I carrie to your worſhip, vnto whom I confeſſe my ſelfe moſt wholie bounden, and leaſt my rude ſpeeches ſhould ſauor of flatterie. I here leaue your worſhip to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who ſend you health and heauen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips moſt dutifull to command, THOMAS SAVNDERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1780:4"/>
            <head>To the gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>GEntle Reader, I haue here preſented to thy vew, (although of my ſelfe altogether vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yet wonne with the earneſtneſſe of ſuch (my friendes) as I might not withſtand) the true reporte of my troubles and of diuers others my Companions and fellowes in <hi>Tripolie,</hi> vnder the <hi>Turkes</hi> dominion, which I had thought at the firſt ſetting downe in paper, ſhould neuer haue bin put in print, but notwithſtanding now, I commit it to thy fauourable conſideration, and (I hope) to thy benefit and good liking. Beſeeching thee to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me for ſuch faultes as I haue groſelie ouerſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, conſidering alwaies that trueth needeth no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led termes: If there be anie thing that deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee I haue my deſire, if otherwiſe, friendlie controule, and then wil I reſt content, and ſo farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to vſe, Thomas Saunders.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1780:4"/>
            <head>OF A MOST LAMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table voiage made into Trypolie in Barbarie, in a Ship called the IESVS, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THis voiage was ſet foorth by the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful, ſir <hi>Edward Oſburne</hi> knight, cheefe merchant of all the Turkiſh companie, &amp; one maiſter <hi>Richard Stapers,</hi> the ſhip being of the burthen of one hundred tun, called the <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſhée was builded at <hi>Farmne</hi> a riuer by <hi>Portſmoth,</hi> The owners were M. <hi>Thomas Thomſon, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Carnabie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn Gilman.</hi> The Maiſter (vnder God) was one <hi>Aches Hellier</hi> of <hi>Blackwall,</hi> and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mate was one <hi>Richard Morris</hi> of that place: their Pilot was one <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Ierado</hi> a French man, of the Prouince of <hi>Maſſillins:</hi> the Purſer was one <hi>William Thomſon</hi> our owners ſon, the marchants factors were <hi>Romaine Sonnings</hi> a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and <hi>Richard Skegs,</hi> ſeruant vnto the ſaid maiſter <hi>Stapers:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> owners were bound vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts by charter partie thereupon, in one thouſand marks, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaid ſhip by Gods permiſſion ſhould go for <hi>Tripoly</hi> in <hi>Barbarie:</hi> that is to ſaie, firſt from <hi>Portſmouth</hi> to <hi>Newhauen</hi> in <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die:</hi> from thence to ſaint <hi>Lukar,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>S. Lucas</hi> in <hi>Andeloſeer,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Tripolie,</hi> which is in the eaſt part of <hi>Affrica,</hi> and ſo to returne vnto <hi>London.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Man dooth purpoſe, and God dooth diſpoſe.</note> But héere ought euerie Chriſtian to note &amp; conſider the workes of our God (that manie times) what man dooth determine
<pb facs="tcp:1780:5"/> God dooth diſappoint. The ſaid maiſter hauing ſome occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to go to <hi>Farmne,</hi> tooke with him the Pilot and the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and returning againe, by meanes of a perrie of winde, the bote wherein they were, was drowned: the ſaid Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">The Maiſter and the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer with all the reſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Pilot drowned.</note> the Purſſer, and all the companie, onelie the ſaid Pilot by experience in ſwimming ſaued himſelfe: theſe were the beginning of our ſorrowes. After which the ſaid Maiſters mate would not procéed in that voiage: and the owners hearing of this miſfortune, and the vnwillingneſſe of the Maiſters mate, did ſend downe one <hi>Richard Deimound,</hi> and ſhipped him for Maiſter,<note place="margin">A new Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter choſen.</note> who did chooſe for his Mate one <hi>Andrew Dier,</hi> and ſo the ſaid ſhip departed on hir voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age accordinglie: that is to ſaie, about the ſixtéenth daie of October, in <hi>anno</hi> 1584, ſhée made ſaile from <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and the eightéenth day then next following,<note place="margin">The new m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſter died. The Ieſus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued into Newhauen. Another Maſter choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſhée arriued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Newhauen,</hi> where our ſaid laſt maiſter <hi>Richard Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mound</hi> by a ſurfeit died. The factors then appointed the ſaid <hi>Andrew Dier,</hi> being then Maiſters mate, to be their Maiſter for that voiage, who did chooſe to be his Mates, the two quarter maiſters of the ſame Ship, to wit, <hi>Peter Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> and <hi>Giles Shillabey,</hi> and for Purſer was ſhipped ane <hi>Richard Burges,</hi> afterward about the eight daie of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, we made ſaile foorthward, and by force of weather we were driuen backe againe into <hi>Portſmouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ieſus driuen backe ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine into Portſmouth.</note> where we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed our victuals and other neceſſaries, &amp; then the wind came faire. About the nine and twentith daie then next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, we departed thence: &amp; the firſt day of December, by means of a contrarie wind,<note place="margin">After ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine into Plimmouth. After that driuen backe to Falmouth.</note> we were driuen to <hi>Plimmouth:</hi> the xviii. day then next following, we made foorthward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, &amp; by force of wether we were driuen into <hi>Falmouth,</hi> where we remained vntill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt day of Ianuary: at which time the wind came faire, we departed thence, &amp; about the xx. day of the ſaid moneth, we ariued ſafelie at <hi>S. Lucas,</hi> and about the ix. day of March next following, we made ſaile fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, &amp; about the xviii. daie of the ſame moneth we came to <hi>Tripolie</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ieſus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued into Tripolie.</note> in <hi>Barbarie,</hi> where we were verie well inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrie, &amp; alſo of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place is ſwéet oiles: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king there is a marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:1780:5"/> and the rather willing to preferre himſelfe before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, requeſted our ſaid factors to trafike with him,<note place="margin">The king of Tripolie a marchant.</note> and promiſed them that if they would take his oiles at his owne price, they ſhould paie no maner of cuſtome, and they tooke of him certeine Tuns of Oile: &amp; afterward percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that they might haue far better cheape, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cuſtome frée, they deſired the King to licence them to take the Oiles at the pleaſure of his commons, for that his price did exceed theirs: wherevnto the king would not agree, but was rather contented to abate his price: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the factors bought all their Oiles of the Kings cuſtome free, and ſo laded the ſame aboord.</p>
            <p>In the meane time there came to that place one <hi>Miles Dickenſon,</hi> in a Ship of <hi>Briſtow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Another ſhip of Briſtowe came to Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polie.</note> who togither with our ſaid factors, tooke a houſe to themſelues there Our French factor <hi>Romaine Sonnings,</hi> deſirous to buie a commoditie in the market, and wanting monie, deſired the ſaid <hi>Miles Dickenſon</hi> to lend him a hundred <hi>Chikinoes</hi> vntill he came to his lodging, which he did,<note place="margin">A French fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor beguiled an Engliſh factor.</note> and afterward the ſame <hi>Sonnings</hi> met with <hi>Miles Dickenſon</hi> in the ſtréet, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him monie bound vp in a napkin: ſaieng, maiſter <hi>Dickenſon</hi> there is the monie that I borowed of you, and ſo thanked him for the ſame: he doubting nothing leſſe then falſhood, which is ſildome knowne among marchants, &amp; ſpeciallie being togither in one houſe, &amp; is the more deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able betwéen Chriſtians, then being in Turkie among the heathen: the ſaid <hi>Dickenſon</hi> did not tell the monie preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, vntill he came to his lodging, and then finding nine <hi>Chikinoes</hi> lacking of his hundred, which was aboue three pounds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for that euerie <hi>Chikinoe</hi> is worth ſeauen ſhillings of Engliſh monie: he came to the ſaid <hi>Romaine Sonnings</hi> and deliuered him his handkercher, and aſked him how manie <hi>Chikinoes</hi> he had deliuered him, <hi>Sonnings</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, a hundred: <hi>Dickenſon</hi> ſaid no: and ſo they proteſted and ſwore on both parts: but in the end the ſaid <hi>Romaine Sonnings</hi> did ſweare deepelie with deteſtable othes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">The French factor deſired vengeance to light on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which God brought to paſſe for an example to bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phemous ſwearers.</note> and curſſes, and praied God that he might ſhew his works on him, that other might take enſample thereby, and that he
<pb facs="tcp:1780:6"/> might be hanged like a Dog, and neuer come into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land againe, if he did not deliuer vnto the ſaid <hi>Dickenſon</hi> an hundred <hi>Chekinoes.</hi> And héere beholde a notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for all blaſphemers, curſſers, and ſwearers, how GOD rewarded him accordinglie, for manie times it commeth to paſſe, that GOD ſheweth his miracles vpon ſuch monſtrous blaſphemers, to the inſample of others, as now héereafter you ſhall héere what befell to this <hi>Romaine Sonnings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a man in the ſaid Towne a pledge, whoſe name was <hi>Patrone Norado,</hi> who the yeare before had doone this <hi>Sonnings</hi> ſome pleaſure there. The foreſaid <hi>Patrone Norado</hi> was indebted vnto a Turke of that Towne, in the ſumme of foure hundred and fiftie crownes, for certeine goods ſent by him into Chriſtendome in a Ship of his owne, and by his owne brother, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe remained in <hi>Tripolie</hi> as pledge, vntill his ſaid brothers returne: and as the reporte went there, that after his brothers arriuall into Chriſtendome, hee came among lewde companie,<note place="margin">A conſpiracie practiſed by the French Factor, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of 450 crownes.</note> and loſte his brothers ſaid Ship and goods at dice, and neuer returned vnto him againe. The ſaid <hi>Patrone Norado</hi> being voide of all hope, and finding nowe opportunitie, conſulted with the ſaid <hi>Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> for to ſwimme a ſeaboord the Ilands, and the Ship being then out of danger, ſhould take him in, as after was confeſſed, and ſo to goe to <hi>Tallowne</hi> in the prouince of <hi>Maſſillins,</hi> with this <hi>Patrone Norado,</hi> and there to take in the reſt of his lading. The Ship being readie the firſt daie of Maie, and hauing hir Sailes all abroad, our ſaid Factors did take their leaue of the King, who verie courteouſlie bid them farewell, and when they came aboord, they commanded the Maiſter and the companie haſtelie to get out the Ship: the Maiſter anſwered that it was vnpoſſible, for that the winde was contrarie and ouerblowed. And hee required vs vpon forfeiture of our bands, that we ſhould doo our indeuour to get hir foorth, then went we to warpe out the Ship, and preſentlie the king ſent a bote aboord of vs, with thrée men in hir, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding
<pb facs="tcp:1780:6"/> the ſaid <hi>Sonnings</hi> to come a ſhore: at whoſe comming, the King demanded of him cuſtome for the Oiles,<note place="margin">The king of Tripolie ſwarueth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his promiſe, through co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe.</note> 
               <hi>Sonnings</hi> aunſwered him that his highneſſe had promiſed to deliuer them cuſtome frée: but notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the king weighed not his ſaid promiſe, and as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell that hath not the feare of GOD before his eies, nor regarde of his word, albeit he was a King: he cauſed the ſaid <hi>Sonnings</hi> to paie the cuſtome to the vttermoſt pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. And afterward willed him to make haſte awaie, ſaieng, that the <hi>Ienizaries</hi> would haue the Oile a ſhore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Theſe <hi>Ienizaries</hi> are ſouldiours there vnder the Great Turke, and their power is aboue the Kings. And ſo the ſaid Factor departed from the King, and came to the water ſide, and called for a bote to come a boorde, and hee brought with him the foreſaid <hi>Patrone Norado.</hi> The companie inquiſitiue to know what man that was,<note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their troubles, and occaſion of all their miſerie.</note> 
               <hi>Sonnings</hi> aunſwered, that he was his countriman, a paſſenger: I praie GOD ſaid the Companie, that we come not into trouble by this man. Then ſaid <hi>Sonnings</hi> angerlie, what haue you to doo with anie matters of mine, if anie thing chaunce otherwiſe then well, I muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for all.</p>
            <p>Nowe the Turke vnto whome this <hi>Patrone Norado</hi> was indebted, miſſing him, ſuppoſed him to be aboord of our Ship, and preſentlie went vnto the King, and told him that he thought that his pledge <hi>Patrone Norado</hi> was aboord of the Engliſh Ship, wherevpon the King preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſent a bote aboord of vs, with thrée men in hir, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the ſaid <hi>Sonnings</hi> to come a ſhore, and not ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anie thing as touching the man, he ſaid that he would come preſentlie in his owne bote, but aſſoone as they were gone, hee willed vs to warpe foorth the Ship, and ſaid that hee woulde ſée the knaues hanged before he would goe a ſhore. And when the King ſaw that hee came not a ſhore, but ſtill continued warping awaie the Ship, he ſtraight commanded the Gunner of the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke next vnto vs, to ſhoote thrée ſhootes without ball.
<pb facs="tcp:1780:7"/> Then we came all to the ſaid <hi>Sonnings,</hi> and aſked of him what the matter was, that we were ſhot at, he ſaid that it was the <hi>Ienezaries</hi> would haue the oile a ſhore againe, and willed vs to make haſt awaie,<note place="margin">All the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h gunners in T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie commanded to doo their beſt to ſinke the IESVS, but could n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> once hit hir.</note> and after that he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged thrée ſhots without ball, he command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d all the gunners in the towne to doo their indeuoure to ſinke vs, but the Turkiſh gunners could not once ſtrike vs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the king ſent preſentlie to the <hi>Baneo:</hi> this <hi>Baneo</hi> is the priſon whereas all the captiues laie at night, and promiſed if that there were anie that could either ſinke vs, or elſe cauſe vs to come in againe, he ſhould haue a hundred crownes and his libertie. With that came foorth a Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard called <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A proclam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer could ſinke hir, or bring hir in ſhould haue a C. crownes, &amp; if he were a captiue he ſhould haue his libertie. How a Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard tooke it in hand, and brought it to paſſe, &amp; made the Ship to yeeld.</note> which had béene an old ſeruitor in Flanders, and he ſaid, that vpon performance of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, he would vndertake either to ſinke vs, or to cauſe vs to come in againe, and thereto he would gage his life, and at the firſt ſhot he ſplyt our Rothers head in peeces, and the ſecond ſhot he ſtrake vs vnder water, and the third ſhot he ſhot vs through our foremaſt with a Coluerlyn ſhot, &amp; thus he hauing rent both our Rother &amp; Maſt, and ſhot vs vnder water, we were inforced to go in againe. This <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> for all his diligence héerein, had neither his libertie nor an hundred crownes, ſo promiſed by the ſaid king, but after his ſeruice doone, was committed againe to priſon, wherby may appeare the regard that a Turke or Infidell hath of his woord, although he be able to performe it, yea more, though he be a King.</p>
            <p>Then our marchants ſéeing no remedie, they toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with fiue of our companie went a ſhore, and then they ceaſed ſhooting, they ſhot vnto vs in the whole nine and thirtie ſhootes, without the hurt of anie man. And when our marchants came a ſhore, the king comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded preſentlie that they with the reſt of our companie, that were with them ſhould be cheined foure and foure, to a hundred waight of iron,<note place="margin">The Engliſh men cheined by foure and foure.</note> and when we came in with the ſhip, there came preſentlie aboue an hundred Turkes aboord of vs, and they ſearched vs, &amp; ſtript our verie clothes from our backs, and brake open our cheſts and made
<pb facs="tcp:1780:7"/> a ſpoile of all that we had: and the Chriſtian caitifes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that ſame a boord of vs, made ſpoile of our goods, and vſed vs as ill as the Turkes did. And our Maiſters mate hauing a <hi>Geneua</hi> Bible in his hand,<note place="margin">The Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> captiues as greedie of the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens ſpoile as the Turks.</note> there came the kings chaefe gunner, and tooke it out from him, who ſhewed me of it, and I hauing the language, went preſentlie to the kings treaſurer, and told him of it: ſaieng, that ſith it was the will of God that we ſhould fall into their hands, yet that they ſhould graunt vs to vſe our conſciences to our owne diſcretion, as they ſuffered the Spaniards and other nations to vſe theirs, and he granted vs, then I told him that the maiſter gunner had taken awaie a Bible from one of our men, the Treaſurer went preſentlie and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to deliuer vp the Bible againe, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h he did: and within a little after he tooke it from the man againe, and I ſhewed the Treaſuror of it, and preſentlie he commanded him to deliuer it againe: ſaieng, thou villeine, wilt thou turne to chriſtianitie againe, for he was a <hi>Renegoi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Turks tooke a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua Bible for his ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re of the ſpoile.</note> which was one that firſt was a Chriſtian, and afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Turke, and ſo be deliuered me the Bible the ſecond time. And then I hauing it in my hand, the gunner came to me, and ſpake theſe words, ſaieng: thou Dog I will haue the booke in deſpight of thée, and tooke it from me, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng: if thou tell the Kings Treaſurer of it anie more, by Mahummet I will be reuenged of thée. Notwithſtanding I went the third time vnto the Kings Treaſurer, and told him of it, and he came with me, ſaieng this vnto the gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: by the head of the great Turke, if thou take it from him againe, thou ſhalt haue an hundred Baſtanadoes. And foorthwith he deliuered me the booke, ſaieng, he had not the valew of a pin of the ſpoile of the Ship,<note place="margin">All that had ſhare of the ſpoile (ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie after) by Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> which was the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him, as héereafter you ſhall heere, for there was none, neither Chriſtian nor Turke that tooke the valew of a penniworth of our goods from vs, but periſhed both bodie and goods within ſeauentéene months following, as héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall plainelie appeare. Then came the Gwardian Baſhée which is the keeper of the Kinges captiues, to fetch vs all a ſhore, and then I remembring the miſerable eſtate
<pb facs="tcp:1780:8"/> of poore diſtreſſed captiues, in the time of their bondage to thoſe Infidels: went to mine owne cheſt, and tooke out thereof a iarre of Oile, and filled a baſket full of white Ruſke to carrie a ſhore with me, but before I came to the <hi>Banio,</hi> the Turkiſh boies had taken awaie almoſt all my bread, and the kéeper ſaid, deliuer me the iarre of Oile, and when thou commeſt to the <hi>Banio</hi> thou ſhalte haue it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">The lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the marchants and marriners being all cheined in priſon.</note> but I neuer had it of him anie more. But when I came to the <hi>Banio,</hi> and ſawe our marchants and all the reſt of our companie in Cheines, and we all readie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſome reward, what heart in the world is there ſo hard, but would haue pittied our cauſe, hearing or ſeeing the lamentable gréeting there was betwixt vs: all this happened the firſt of Maie.</p>
            <p>And the ſecond daie of the ſame moneth, the King with all his counſell ſat in iudgement vpon vs. The firſt that were had foorth to be reigned,<note place="margin">The Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> were the Factors, and the Maiſters, &amp; the King aſked them wherfore they came not a ſhore when he ſent for them: and <hi>Romaine Sonnings</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that though he were King a ſhore, and might command there, ſo was hee as touching thoſe that were vnder him:<note place="margin">Romaine Sonnings condempned to be hanged ouer one of the Bulwarks. The Maiſter Andrew Dier, condempned to be hanged ouer the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke. Rich. Skegs procured maiſter Diers pardon and his owne.</note> and therefore ſaid, if anie offence be, the fault is wholie in my ſelfe, and in no other. Then foorthwith the King gaue iudgement, that the ſaid <hi>Romaine Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> ſhould be hanged ouer the Northeneſt Bulwarke, from whence hee conueied the forenamed <hi>Patrone No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rado,</hi> and then hee called for our Maiſter <hi>Andrew Dier,</hi> and vſed fewe woordes to him, and ſo condemned him to bee hanged ouer the walles of the Weſtermoſt Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke.</p>
            <p>Then fell our other Factor (named <hi>Richard Skegs</hi>) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his knées before the King, and ſaid, I beſéeche your highneſſe either to pardon our Maiſter, or elſe ſuffer me to die for him, for hee is ignorant of this cauſe. And then the people of that countrie fauouring the ſaide <hi>Richard Skegs,</hi> beſought the King to pardon them bothe. So then the King ſpake theſe wordes: Beholde for thy ſake I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb facs="tcp:1780:8"/> the Maiſter. Then preſentlie the Turkes ſhouted, and cried, ſaieng: Awaie with the Maiſter from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the King. And then hee came into the <hi>Banio</hi> where as wee were, and tolde vs what had happened, and wee all reioiſed at the good happe of maiſter <hi>Skegges,</hi> that hée was ſaued, and our Maiſter for his ſake. But afterwarde our ioye was turned to double ſorrowe, for in the meane time the Kings minde was altered, for that one of his Counſell had aduiſed him, that vnleſſe the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter died alſo, by the lawe they could not confiſcate the Shippe nor goods, neither captiue anie of the men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the King ſent for our Maiſter againe,<note place="margin">Maiſter Dier afterwards condempned to be hanged ouer another Bulwarke.</note> and gaue him another iudgement after his pardon for one cauſe, which was that hee ſhould bee hanged. Heere all true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans maye ſee what truſt a Chriſtian man maie put in an Infidels promiſe, who being a King, and pardoned a man nowe, as you haue heard, and within an houre after han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him for the ſame cauſe before a whole multitude: and alſo promiſed our Factors their Oiles cuſtome frée, and at their going awaye made them paie the vttermoſt pennie for the cuſtome thereof.</p>
            <p>And when that <hi>Romaine Sonnings</hi> ſawe no remedie but that he ſhould dye, bee proteſted to turne Turke,<note place="margin">Romaine Sonnings the French man turned Turke in hope of his life, and died in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Turke.</note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereby to haue ſaued his life. Then ſaid the Turke, if thou wilt turne Turke, ſpeake the wordes that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto belong, and hee did ſo. Then ſaid they vnto him, nowe thou ſhalt die in the faith of a Turke, and ſo he did as the Turkes reported that were at his execution. And the forenamed <hi>Patrone Norado,</hi> whereas before hee had libertie, and did nothing, hee then was condemned ſlaue perpetuall, except there were paiment made of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſumme of monie. Then the King condempned all vs, who were in number ſixe and twentie, of the which, two were hanged as you haue heard,<note place="margin">XXIII. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to perpetuall priſon.</note> and one died the firſt daye wee c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me a ſhore, by the viſitation of almightie God, and the other three and twentie hee condemned ſlaues per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuallie vnto the Great Turke, and the Ship and goods
<pb facs="tcp:1780:9"/> was confiſcated to the cſe of the great Turke: and then we all f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll downe vpon our knees, giuing God thanks for this ſorrowfull viſitation and giuing our ſelues wholie to the almightie powre of GOD, vnto whome all ſecrets are knowne, that he of his goodneſſe would vouchſafe to looke vpon vs. Heere may all true Chriſtian hearts ſee the woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes of God ſhewed vpon ſuch Infidels blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, whooremaiſters, and runnagate Chriſtians, and ſo ſhall you read in the end of this booke, of the like vpon the vnfaithfull king and all his children, and of as manie as tooke anie portion of the ſaid goods. But firſt to ſhew our miſerable bondage and flauerie,<note place="margin">Euerie fiue men allowed but two pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bread in a daie.</note> and vnto what ſmall pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and allowance we were tide, for euerie fiue men had allowance but fiue Oſperes of bread in a day, which is but two pence Engliſh: and our lodging was to lie on the bare boords, with a verie ſimple cape to couer vs, we were alſo forceablie and moſt violentlie ſhauen, head and beard, and within three daies after,<note place="margin">The Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens heads and beards forceablie ſhauen.</note> I and ſix more of my fellowes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with foure ſcore of Italians and Spaniards, were ſent foorth in a Galeat to take a Gréekiſh Carmoſal, which came into <hi>Arrabia</hi> to ſteale Negroes, &amp; went out of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polie</hi> vnto that place, which was two hundred and fortie leagues thence,<note place="margin">The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans cheined, three &amp; three to an Oare in the Galley, and rowed all naked aboue the girdle, &amp; pitti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ullie beaten with a Oxe piſſell,</note> but wée were cheaned thrée and thrée to an oare, and we rowed naked aboue the girdle, and the Bote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaine of the Galley walked abaſt the Maſt and his Mate afore the Maſte, and each of them a Bulles piſſell dried in their handes, and when their diuelliſh choller roſe, they would ſtrike the Chriſtians for no cauſe: and they allowed vs but halfe a pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of bread a man in a day without other kinde of ſuſtenance, water excepted: And when we came to the place whereas we ſaw the Carmoſall, wée were not ſuffered to haue neither needle, bodkin, knife, or any other inſtrument about vs, nor at any other time in the night vp on paine of one hundreth baſtinadoes, wee were then alſo vildely manackled in ſuch ſort, that we coulde not put our handes the length of a foote aſunder the one from the other, and euery night they ſearched our chaines three times, to ſee if they were faſt reaueted: Wee continued fight with the
<pb facs="tcp:1780:9"/> Carmoſall thrée houres, and then we tooke it,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The Gallie of Tripolie tooke a Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Carmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall.</p>
                  <p>The Turkes build a church The Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men put to all kind of ſlauerie. Some to hew ſtones. Some to draw ſtores. Some to draw timber. Some to draw Ordinance. The countrie rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king.</p>
               </note> and loſt but two of our men in that fight, but there were ſlaine of the Greekes fiue, and fourteen were cruellie hurt, and they that were ſound, were preſentlie made ſlaues, and cheined to the oares: and within fiftéene daies after we returned againe into <hi>Tripolie,</hi> and then we were put to all manner of ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, I was put to hew ſtones, and other to carrie ſtones, and ſome to draw the Carte with earth, and ſome to make morter, &amp; ſome to draw ſtones (for at that time the Turkes builded a Church:) and thus we were put to al kind of ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie that was to bée done, and in the time of our béeing there, the Moores that are the Huſbandmen of the countrey rebelled againſt the King, becauſe he would haue conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them to paye greater tribute then heretofore they had doone, ſo that the ſouldiors of <hi>Tripolie</hi> marched foorth of the towne to haue ioined battell againſt the Moores for their rebellion, and the King ſent with them foure peeces of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which were drawne by the captiues twentie miles into the countrie after them, and at the ſight thereof the Moores fled, and then the captaines returned backe againe. Then I and ninetéene Chriſtians more, were ſent twelue miles into the countrie with a cart to lode timber, and we returned againe the ſame daie.<note place="margin">The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſent three times a weeke thirtie miles to fetch wood</note> Nowe the King had eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene captiues, which thrée times a wéeke went to fetch wood thirtie miles from the towne, and on a time he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed me for one of the eighteene, &amp; we departed at eight of the clocke in the night: and vpon the waie as we rode vpon the Cammels, I demanded of one of our companie? who did direct vs the waie, he ſaid that there was a Moore in our companie which was our guide, and I demanded of them how <hi>Tripolie</hi> and the wood bore one of the other, and he ſaid, Eaſt Northeaſt, and Weaſt Southweaſt. And at midnight or neere thereabouts, as I was riding vpon my Cammell, I ſell a ſleepe, and the guide and all the reſt rode awaie from me, not thinking but I had béene among them. When I awooke, and finding my ſelfe alone, durſt not call nor hallow, for feare leaſt the wilde Moores ſhould heare me, becauſe they hold this opinion that in killing a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an they doo God good ſeruice: &amp; muſing with my ſelfe what
<pb facs="tcp:1780:10"/> were beſt for me to doo, and if I ſhould go foorth and the wilde Moores ſhould hap to méet with me, they would kill me: and on the other ſide, if I ſhould returne backe to <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polie</hi> without anie wood or companie, I ſhould be moſt miſerablie vſed therefore: of two euils, rather I had to go foorth to the loſing of my life, then to turne backe and truſt to their mercie, fearing to be vſed as before I had ſeene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: for vnderſtanding by ſome of my companie before, how <hi>Tripolie</hi> and the ſaid wood did lie one of another, by the North ſtarre. I went foorth at aduenture, and as God would haue it, I came right to the place where they were, euen about an houre before day: there altogether we reſted and gaue our Cammels prouender, and aſſoone as the daie appeared,<note place="margin">The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans plucked vp the wood by the roots to loade their Cammels.</note> we rode all into the wood: and I ſéeing no wood there, but a ſticke héere and a ſticke there, about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a mans arme, growing in the ſand, cauſed me to maruell how ſo manie Cammels ſhould be loden in that place. The wood was Iiniper, we néeded no axe nor other edge toole to cut it, but pluckt it vp by ſtrength of hands, rootes and all, which a man might eaſilie doo, and ſo gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it togither, a little at one place and ſo at another; and laded our Cammels, and came home about ſeauen of the clocke that night following: bicauſe I fell lame and my Cammell was tired, I left my wood in the waie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eighteene captiues run awaie from Tripolie.</note>There was in <hi>Tripolie</hi> that time a <hi>Venecian,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Benadetta Veniſſiano,</hi> and ſeauentéene cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues more of his companie, which ran awaie from <hi>Tripo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> in a bote, and came in ſight of an Iland called <hi>Malta,</hi> which lieth fortie leagues from <hi>Tripolie</hi> right North, and being within a mile of the ſhore, and verie faire weather, one of their companie ſaid, <hi>In diſpeto de diu a deſſe a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio de pilliar tarra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God vpon wicked blaſphemers.</note> which is as much to ſay: In the deſpite of God we ſhall now fetch the ſhore, and preſentlie there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe a mightie ſtorme, with thunder and raine, &amp; the wind at North, their bote being verie ſmall, ſo that they were inforced to beare vp rome, &amp; to ſheare right afore the wind oueragainſt the coaſt of <hi>Barbarie</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they came, &amp; rowing vp &amp; downe the coaſt, their vittels being ſpent, the xxi. day after their departure, they were inforced through
<pb facs="tcp:1780:10"/> the want of food to come a ſhore, thinking to haue ſtolne ſome ſhéepe: but the Moores of the countrie verie craftilie, perceiuing their intent gathered togither a thréeſcore horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; hid themſelues behind a ſandie hill, &amp; when the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were come all a ſhore,<note place="margin">The Moores tooke the xviii. chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that ran awaie from Tripolie.</note> &amp; paſt vp halfe a mile into ſhe countrie, the Moores rode betwixt them and their bote, and ſome of them purſued the chriſtians, &amp; ſo they were all ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and brought to <hi>Tripolie,</hi> from whence they had before eſcaped: &amp; preſentlie the king commanded that the foreſaid <hi>Benedicta</hi> with one more of his companie ſhould loſe their eares, &amp; the reſt to be moſt cruellie beaten, which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie doone.<note place="margin">The king of Tripolie had a ſon which was ruler in the Iland of Ierbbye.</note> This king had a ſonne which was a ruler in an Iland called <hi>Ierbby,</hi> wherevnto ariued an Engliſh ſhip called the <hi>Greene Dragon,</hi> of the which was maiſter, one M. <hi>Blonket,</hi> who hauing a verie vnhappie boie in that ſhip, &amp; vnderſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer would turne Turke ſhould be well enterteined of the kings ſonne, this boy did run a ſhore, &amp; voluntarilie turned Turke. Shortlie after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings ſone came to <hi>Tripolie</hi> to viſit his father, &amp; ſéeing our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, he greatlie fancied <hi>Rich. Burges</hi> our purſſer, &amp; <hi>Iames Smith,</hi> they were both yoong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore he was verie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to turne Turke, but they wold not yéeld to his deſire, ſaieng: we are your fathers ſlaues, &amp; as ſlaues we will ſerue him: then his father the king ſent for them, &amp; aſked them if they would turne Turke, &amp; they ſaid: If it pleaſe your highnes, chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s we were borne, &amp; ſo we will remaine, &amp; beſéeched the king that they might not be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thervnto. The king had there before in his houſe, a ſon of a yeoman of our Queenes guard,<note place="margin">The kinges ſonne had a Captiue that was ſonne to one of the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties guard, that was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to turne Turke.</note> whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings ſon had inforſed to turne Turke, his name was <hi>Iohn Nelſon,</hi> him the king cauſed to be brought to theſe yoong men, and then ſaid vnto them: will not you beare this your countriman companie, and be Turke as he is, and they ſaid, that they would not yéeld therevnto during life: but it ſell out, that within a moneth after, the Kinges ſonne went home to <hi>Ierbbïe</hi> againe, being ſixe ſcore miles from <hi>Tripolie,</hi> and caried our two foreſaid yoong men with him, which were <hi>Richard Burges</hi> and <hi>Iames Smith:</hi> and after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from vs, they ſent vs a letter, ſignifieng that there
<pb facs="tcp:1780:11"/> was no violence ſhewed vnto them as not, but within thrée daies after they were violentlie vſed, for that the kings ſonne demanded of them againe if that they would turne Turke:<note place="margin">Richard Bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges made a Turke by force.</note> then anſwered <hi>Richard Burges,</hi> a Chriſtian I am, and ſo I will remaine. Then the Kinges ſonne verie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerlie ſaid vnto him: by Mahommet thou ſhalt preſentlie be made Turke. Then called he for his men, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to make him Turke, and they did ſo, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed him, and would haue had him ſpeake the words that therevnto belonged, but he anſwered them ſtoutlie that hée would not: and although they had put on him the habit of a Turke, yet ſaid hee, Chriſtian I was borne and ſo I will remaine, though you force me to doo otherwiſe. And then he called for the other, &amp; commanded him to be made Turke perforce alſo:<note place="margin">Iames Smith made Turke, and circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by force.</note> but he was verie ſtrong, for it was ſo much as eight of the Kings ſonnes men could doo to hold him, ſo in the end they circumciſed him, and made him Turke. Now to paſſe ouer a little, and ſo to ſhew the maner of our deliuerie out of that miſerable captiuitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for thoſe Engliſhmens deliuerie.</note>In Maye aforeſaid, ſhortlie after our apprehenſion, I wrote a letter into England vnto my Father dwelling in Eauiſtoke in Deuonſhire, ſignifieng vnto him the whole eſtate of our calamities: and I wrote alſo to <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> to the Engliſh ambaſſadour, both which letters were faithfullie deliuered. But when my Father had receiued my letter, and vnderſtood the truth of our miſhap; and the occaſion thereof, and what had happened to the offendors: he certified the Right honorable the earle of Bedford there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, who in ſhorte ſpace acquainted hir Highneſſe with the whole cauſe thereof, and hir Maieſtie like a moſt mercifull Princeſſe, tendring hir ſubiects, preſentlie tooke order for our deliuerance. Wherevpon the right worſhipfull ſir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Oſburne,</hi> knight, directed his letters with all ſpeed to the Engliſh ambaſſadour in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to procure our deliuerie, and he obteined the great Turks commiſſion, &amp; ſent it forth with to <hi>Tripolie,</hi> by one maſter <hi>Edward Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> togither with a Iuſtice of the great Turks, &amp; one ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dior, and another Turke, &amp; a Greeke which was his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretor, which could ſpeake beſides Gréeke, Turkiſh, Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:1780:11"/> Spaniſh, &amp; Engliſh. And when they came to <hi>Tripolie,</hi> they were well interteined.<note place="margin">A Commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come from the great Turke for the Engliſhmens deliuerie.</note> And the firſt night they did lie in a captaines houſe in the towne, all our companie that were in <hi>Tripolie,</hi> came that night for ioy to maiſter <hi>Barton</hi> and the other commiſſioners to ſee them. Then maiſter <hi>Barton</hi> ſaid vnto vs, welcome my good countrimen, and louinglie inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined vs, &amp; at our departure from him, he gaue vs two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and ſaid, ſerue God, for to morrow I hope you ſhall be as frée as euer you were, we all giue him thankes, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. The next daie in the morning verie earlie, the king had intelligence of their comming, ſent word to the kéeper, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none of the Engliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (meaning our companie) ſhould go to worke. Then he ſent for maiſter <hi>Barton</hi> and the other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, &amp; demanded of the ſaid M <hi>Barton</hi> his meſſage: the Iuſtice anſwered, that the Great Turke his Souereigne had ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him,<note place="margin">The ſomme of the great Turkes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by a a Turkiſh Iuſtice.</note> ſignifieng that he was informed that a certeine Engliſh ſhip called the <hi>Ieſus</hi> was by him the ſaid King confiſcated, about twelue moneths ſince, and now my ſaid Souereigne hath héere ſent his eſpeciall commiſſion by vs vnto you for the deliuerie of the ſaid ſhip &amp; goods, and alſo the free libertie &amp; deliuerance of the Engliſhmen of the ſame ſhip, whom you haue taken and kept in captiuitie &amp; farther the ſame Iuſtice ſaid, I am authoriſed by my ſaid ſouereigne the great Turke to ſee it doone: and therefore I command you by vertue of this commiſſion, preſentlie to make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the premiſes or the value therof, and ſo did the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces deliuer vnto the King the great Turkes commiſſion to the effect aforeſaid, which commiſſion the king with all obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience receiued: &amp; after the peruſing of the ſame,<note place="margin">The Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men releaſed by the king of Tripolie, and deliuered to M Barton, the 28 daie of Aprill, 1585.</note> he forthwith commanded all the Engliſh captiues to bee brought before him, &amp; then willed the kéeper to ſtrike of all our irons, which doone, the king ſaid. You Engliſhmen for that you did offend the lawes of this place, by the ſame lawes therefore ſome of your companie were condemned to die as you know &amp; you to be perpetuall captiues during your liues: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſeeing it hath pleaſed my ſouereigne lord the great Turke to pardon your ſaid offences, &amp; to giue you your freedom &amp; liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, behold héere I make deliuerie of you to this Engliſh gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman: ſo he deliuered vs all that were there, being thirteene
<pb facs="tcp:1780:12"/> in number, to maiſter <hi>Barton,</hi> who required alſo thoſe two yoong men which the kings ſonne had taken with him. Then the king anſwered that it was againſt their lawe to deliuer them, for that they were turned Turkes: and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſhip and goods, the king ſaid, that he had ſold hir, but would make reſtitution of the value, and as much of the goods as came vnto his hands, and ſo the King aroſe &amp; went to dinner, and commanded a Iew to go with maiſter <hi>Barton</hi> and the other commiſſioners, to ſhewe them their lodging, which was a houſe prouided and appointed them by the ſaid king. And bicauſe I had the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> toongs, by which their moſt trafike in that countrie is, Maiſter <hi>Barton</hi> made me his Cater to buie his victuals for him and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and deliuered me money néedfull for the ſame. Thus were we ſet at libertie, the xxviii. day of Aprill, 1585.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The plagues and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that happened to the king and his people.</note>Now to returne to the kings plagues and puniſhments which Almightie God at his will and pleaſure ſendeth vpon men in the ſight of the world, and likewiſe of the plagues that befell his children and others aforeſaid. Firſt when we were made bondmen, being the ſecond day of May, 1584, the king had 300 captiues, and before the moneth was expired there died of them of the plague 150,<note place="margin">150 captiues died of the plague in one moneth. Nine of the companie of the Ieſus died of the pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gue. The king loſt 150 Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels, taken by the wilde Moores. A captiue of Malta ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie with a Brigandine, and xii. cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues more. The kings faireſt M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vnder him, which he made to be burried in hir ſkinne, ſhooes &amp; all.</note> &amp; whereas there were xxvi. men of our companie, of whom two were hanged, and one died the ſame day that we were made bondſlaues, &amp; that preſent moneth there died nine more of our companie of the plague, &amp; other two were forced to turne Turkes as before is rehearſed: &amp; on the fourth day of Iune next following, the king loſt 150 Cammels, which were taken from him by the wild Moores: &amp; on the xxviii. day of the ſaid moneth of Iune, one <hi>Geffrey Maltees</hi> a <hi>Runnagado</hi> of <hi>Malta,</hi> ran awaie to his countrie, and ſtole a <hi>Brigandine</hi> which the king had buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for to take chriſtians withall, &amp; carried with him twelue chriſtians more which were the kings captiues. Afterward about the tenth day of Iulye next following, the king rode foorth vpon the greateſt &amp; faireſt Mare that might be ſéene, as white as any Swan, he had not ridden fortie paces from his houſe, but on a ſudden the ſame Mare fell downe vnder him ſtarke dead, &amp; I with ſix more was commanded to burie hir ſkin, ſhooes and all, which we did. And about thrée moneths
<pb facs="tcp:1780:12"/> after our deliuerie, M. <hi>Barton</hi> with all the reſidue of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie departed from <hi>Tripolie</hi> to <hi>Oezant</hi> in a veſſell called a <hi>Settea</hi> of one <hi>Marcus Segoorus,</hi> who dwelt in <hi>Oeza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> &amp; after our ariuall at <hi>Oeza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> we remained xv. daies there aboord our veſſell before we could haue <hi>Platego</hi> (that is, leaue to come a ſhore) bicauſe the plague was in that place from whence we came: &amp; about thrée daies after we came a ſhore,<note place="margin">Two Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men ſhipped to Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople with M. Barton. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne of the Engliſhmen ſhipped to England. The Soldiors of Tripolie kill the king. The kings ſonne goeth to Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople with his fathers captiues, who ſkirmiſh in the Galley with him and his Turkes, in which conflict, two Engliſhmen were ſlaine.</note> thether came another <hi>Settea</hi> of <hi>Maſſilins</hi> bound for <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Then did M. <hi>Barton</hi> and his companie, with two more of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, ſhip themſelues as paſſengers in the ſame <hi>Settea,</hi> and went to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> But the other nine of vs that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in <hi>Oeza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> about three moneths after ſhipt our ſelues in a Ship of the ſaid <hi>Mareus Segoorus,</hi> which came to <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zant,</hi> and was bound for England. In which three moneths the Souldiors of <hi>Tripolie</hi> killed the ſaid King. And then the kings ſonne according to the cuſtome there, went to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> to ſurrender vp all his fathers treaſure, goods, Captiues, and Concubines, vnto the Great Turke, and tooke with him our ſaid Purſſer <hi>Richard Burges,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iames Smith,</hi> and alſo the other two Engliſhmen, which he the ſaid kings ſonne had inforced to become Turkes as is aforeſaid. And they the ſaid Engliſhmen, finding now ſome opportunitie, concluded with the Chriſtian captiues which were going with them vnto <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> being in number about one hundred and fiftie, to kill the kings ſonne, and all the Turks which were aboord of the Galley, and priuilie the ſaid Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen conueyed vnto the ſaid Chriſtian captiues weapons for that purpoſe. And when they came into the maine ſea to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (vpon the faithfull promiſe of the ſaid Chriſtian captiues) theſe foure Engliſhmen lept ſuddenlie into the <hi>Crooſſia,</hi> that is, into the midſt of the Galley where the Cannon lieth, and with their ſwords drawne, did fight againſt all the foreſaid Turkes, and for wante of helpe of the ſaid Chriſtian captiues, who falſlie brake the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the ſaid M. <hi>Blonkets</hi> boy was killed, and the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes Smith</hi> &amp; our Purſſer <hi>Richard Burges,</hi> and the other Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, were taken &amp; bound into chaines to be han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there arriuall into Conſtantinoples and as the Lords w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two daies after, paſſing through the gulfe of V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1780:13"/> an Iland called <hi>Saffalonea,</hi> they met with two of the doke of <hi>Venis</hi> his Galleis,<note place="margin">Two Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leis of Venice tooke the king of Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>polie hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the kings ſonne and all the Turkes in it, &amp; releaſed all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, being in number 150.</note> which tooke that Gallie, &amp; kild y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings ſonne, &amp; his mother, &amp; all the Turks that were there, in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>50, and they ſaued the Chriſtian captiues, &amp; would haue killed the two Engliſhmen, bicauſe they were circumciſed &amp; become Turkes, had not the other Chriſtian captiues excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, ſaieng, that they were enforſed to be Turks by the kings ſonne, &amp; ſhewed the <hi>Venecians</hi> alſo, how they did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe at ſea to fight againſt all the Turks &amp; that their two fellowes were ſlaine in that fight. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Venecians</hi> ſaued them, &amp; they with all the reſidue of the ſaid captiues had their libertie, which were in number 150 or thereabouts, &amp; the ſaid Gallie &amp; all the Turkes treaſure, was confiſcated to the vſe of the duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence our two Engliſhmen tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled homeward by land, &amp; in this meane time we had one more of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie which died in <hi>Oezante,</hi> &amp; afterward the other eight ſhipped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues at <hi>Oezante,</hi> in a ſhip of the ſaid <hi>Marcus Segorius</hi> which was bound for Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: &amp; before we departed thence, there ariued the <hi>Aſſencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> &amp; the <hi>George Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauenture</hi> of London into <hi>Saffalonea,</hi> in a harbor ther called <hi>Arrogoſtoria,</hi> whoſe marchants agréed with the marchants of our ſhip, &amp; ſo loded all the marchandize of our ſhip into the ſaid ſhips of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who tooke vs eight alſo in as paſſengers, &amp; ſo we came home, &amp; within two moneths after our ariuall at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſaid purſſer <hi>Richard Burges</hi> &amp; his fellow came home alſo, for the which we are bound to praiſe almightie God during our life, and as dutie bindeth vs, to praie for the preſeruation of our moſt gratious Quéene, for the great care hir Maieſtie had ouer vs hir poore ſubiects, in ſéeking &amp; procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our deliuerance aforeſaid, &amp; alſo for hir honorable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie councell, &amp; I eſpeciallie for the proſperitie &amp; good eſtate of the houſe of the late deceaſed the Right honorable the erle of Bedford, whoſe honor I muſt confeſſe, moſt diligentlie at the ſute of my father now departed, trauelled herein: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Areſt continuallie bounden to his, whoſe ſoule I doubt not but is alreadie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauens in ioy with the Almightie, vnto which place he vouchſafe to bring vs all, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for our ſins ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red moſt vile and ſhamefull death vpon the croſſe, there to liue perpetuallie world without end: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thom Sanders.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1780:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
